Hello English learners and welcome to
another great podcast with English pod.
My name is Marco and I'm Erica.
And today we have another really
great lesson for you, elementary lesson.
That's right and it's
another lesson about money.
We have no money here at
English pod, we are in debt.
In debt.
Yes.
Okay, debt.
So what does that mean,
why don't you tell us?
If I owe you money, I'm in debt.
In debt.
In fact, I think I am in debt to you.
You owe me $250 for a Coke Zero today.
That's true.
All right.
Okay, so let's get started.
Let's take a look at
our vocabulary preview.
vocabulary preview.
We have two words today in our vocabulary
preview and the first one is recession.
Recession.
So recession, everyone's talking about
it right now and what does it mean?
I don't know.
That's your job.
I really don't know.
Why don't you tell me, Erica,
because this isn't my topic for today.
Okay.
Recession is a period of time when
the economy of a country is doing badly.
Inter recession, the country
is making less money.
That's true.
You can give a few
examples of things that
happen in a recession to show
the meaning of this a little bit better.
Right.
So, for example, in a
recession, many people
lose their jobs because companies
might close or go bankrupt.
Exactly.
And also, people start spending less money.
That's true.
And the stock prices
of companies fall pretty.
Pretty dreadful.
Yeah.
They fall a lot.
It's done now in the United States.
Very true.
Okay.
So, let's take a look at our second
word and it has to do with recession.
It's broke.
Broke.
I'm broke.
It means that you have no money.
You're broke.
I'm broke.
Right.
So, these are our two
words for vocabulary preview
today and you're going
to hear them in dialogue.
This dialogue is about
a man who is in debt.
He's broke.
Let's find out what happens.
I'm here to see Mr. Corleone.
I'm really sorry to trouble
you, but I need your help.
Anything for you, Johnny, your
father was like a brother to me.
Well, sir, you see, this
recession has hit me pretty hard.
I lost my job and I'm in a lot of debt.
I see.
Yeah.
You know, I've got credit card bills, card
payments, I've got to pay my mortgage.
And on top of all that, I have
to pay my son's college tuition.
So, you're asking for a loan?
Well, I just thought maybe
you could help me out.
What?
Anytime like this, I'm broke too, you know.
You're not the only one
who's been hit by the recession.
I lost half my money in the stock
market crash, go on, get out of here.
OK, so that was a bit unexpected.
Yeah, that was certainly strange.
He didn't go to the bank to ask for money.
Did he?
He went to the mob and the mob is broke.
Oh, no, you know it's a bad recession
when even the mob runs out of money.
All right, so why don't we start by
looking at our language takeaway?
Language takeaway.
All right, so for today's
language takeaway,
we have four words from the dialogue
which we think are really important.
Yes.
So why don't we start with the first one?
Loan, loan, loan, loan.
So Erica, tell us about a loan.
What is a loan?
OK, when you borrow money, you get a loan.
A loan is not to be confused
with a loan like by myself.
No, so this is L-O-A-N.
Loan.
Right.
OK, great.
Let's take a look at our second word,
mortgage, mortgage, mortgage, mortgage.
Now this is very common.
I'm sure many of you have mortgages.
What is a mortgage?
A mortgage is a type of a loan.
Basically, it's a loan that
helps you to buy a house.
A house or a property?
Yeah, so this is a funny word.
I mean, there's a strange
mortgage with a T.
Yeah, it has a T in it, but
you don't pronounce it.
You say mortgage, mortgage.
So not more, mortgage.
Not more, mortgage.
More, mortgage.
I had troublespelling that one for
this lesson, so I learned it well now.
OK.
Let's move to our third word today.
Hit me pretty hard.
I think we have some examples that
will help us understand this phrase.
Example one.
By divorce, hit me pretty hard.
I'm so depressed.
Example two.
This code has hit me pretty hard.
I've been in bed for a week.
Example three.
The news of Fluffy's
death hit me pretty hard.
I've been crying for days.
OK, so that's a lot clear.
Yeah, great.
Why don't we take a look at our
last word for language takeaway?
Tuition.
So this is the money you have to pay to
your school so that you can study there.
Right.
Usually it's in college,
right, or university.
Yeah, but sometimes in some countries,
you have to pay tuition for public school.
OK, great, so it's time to
listen to our dialogue again.
And it's going to be
slower so we can listen
to all the words that
we just talked about.
Hello.
I'm here to see Mr. Corleone.
Right this way, sir.
Charlie, what can I do for you?
Mr. Corleone.
I'm really sorry to trouble
you, but I need your help.
Anything for you, Charlie, your
father was like a brother to me.
Well, sir, you see, this
recession has hit me pretty hard.
I lost my job and I'm in a lot of debt.
I see.
Yeah, you know, I've got
credit card bills, car payments.
I've got to pay my
mortgage and on top of all
that, I have to pay my
son's college tuition.
So you're asking for a loan?
Well, I just thought maybe
you could help me out.
What?
At a time like this, I'm
broke too, you know.
You're not the only one who
has been hit by the recession.
I lost half my money in
the stock market crash.
Go on, get out of here.
Okay, so I think a lot
of the key language
we just talked about
is a lot more clear now.
But you know, I also noticed some really
interesting phrases in this dialogue.
Yes, I did too.
So let's start with Fluency Builder.
Fluency Builder.
Fluency Builder is a tool that we
use to help you sound more native.
Right, so you can sound more
natural when you're speaking.
So we take a really common phrase
and we show you some great natural ways
of expressing that same idea.
Exactly, and today we have
three of these examples.
Let's start with the first one.
So this phrase we use when we
want to ask somebody, can I help you?
What can I do for you?
Yeah, that sounds really,
really polite and really natural.
Right, so instead of saying, can I help
you or, I don't know, what do you need?
We can just say, what can I do for you?
Exactly.
So let's move to our second phrase.
This phrase we use when we need something.
When we want to say,
I'm sorry to bother you.
Or I'm sorry to interrupt.
Okay, let's listen.
I'm really sorry to trouble you.
I'm sorry to trouble you.
This phrase might be a little bit more
difficult to understand how it's used.
But we've got some examples.
Yes, so let's listen.
Example one.
Can I trouble you for a moment?
I just need you to sign this form for me.
Example two.
I'm sorry to trouble you, but
may I go home early today?
Example three.
Can I trouble you for a pen?
Mine is not working anymore.
Okay, so now let's take a look at
our last phrase for Fluency Builder.
On top of all that.
This is a really useful phrase.
Marko, how would you use it?
Well, for example, today I lost my job.
Oh no, my car got stolen.
Oh my God.
And on top of all that, my
girlfriend broke up with me.
That was a terrible day, it was.
But don't worry, you can use
this phrase also in a positive way.
That's true, you could say.
So today was a really great day.
It was my birthday and all
my friends came to visit me
and on top of all that,
I got a million presents.
That is a great day.
So you can use on top
of all that in this way.
It's like, and also.
And also, yeah, so on top of all that.
So we are ready to listen
to our dialogue a third time.
We can hear all the words
that we just talked about
in all the phrases and you'll definitely
be able to understand a lot better now.
(upbeat music)
- Hello, I'm here to see Mr. Corleone.
- Right this way, sir.
(upbeat music)
- Johnny, what can I do before you?
- Mr. Corleone, I'm really sorry to
trouble you, but I need your help.
- Anything before you, Johnny.
Your father was like a brother to me.
- Well, sir, you see, this
recession has hit me pretty hard.
I lost my job and I'm in a lot of debt.
- I see.
- Yeah, you know,
I've got credit card bills,
card payments, I've
got to pay my mortgage.
And on top of all that, I have
to pay my son's college tuition.
- So you're asking for a loan.
- Well, I just thought maybe
you could help me out.
- But anytime like this,
I'm broke too, you know?
You're not the only one
who's been hit by the recession.
I lost half my money in
the stock market crash.
Go on, get out of here.
(upbeat music)
- Today's dialogue was all
about being in debt, right?
- Yes.
- And different people have different attitudes,
or different viewpoints on being in debt.
- Yes, that's true.
For example, in North America and
in Canada, it's a really common thing.
- Yeah, it's actually
almost good to be in debt.
It's more than good, it's
necessary to be in debt.
- That's right, unless you
have a history of being in debt
and regularly paying off your debts,
you can't actually borrow money.
You can't get a mortgage, you can't
get a car loan, so you can buy a new car.
- Right, that's called a credit history.
So you must have a good credit history
in order to be able to, like you
say, buy a car or buy a house.
- Yeah, and you know, the funny thing is,
when I was in university,
maybe I was 18 years old,
the first thing that happened
at university was banks came
to our university and started
offering you credit cards.
So you can get a credit card
when you're 18, no problem.
- And not only do they
offer you credit cards,
they give you free gifts if
you sign up for a credit card.
- I know they really want
you to have a credit card.
Of course, they want you to
spend more money, that's the trick.
- Yeah, but you know what?
It's totally different
in Europe, for example.
I used to live in Switzerland, and
they're really careful with debts.
Like, it's a bad thing to be in debt.
- Well, yeah, I mean, it's
bad to be in debt, definitely.
- For example, if I wanna have
a credit card in Switzerland,
and let's say I want to
have a limit of 500 francs
that I can spend every month, I need
to put in my bank account 700 francs
before I can even spend
that credit card money.
So it's totally opposite
from North America.
- Well, yeah, I mean, in North America,
it's crazy the way that people are in debt
and it's showing now
with the recession, right?
- Yeah, that's true.
- So everyone be sure to
handle your money carefully,
don't be in debt, unless
you really, really have to.
- Good financial advice from English pod.
- English pod, financial advising service.
- Okay, everyone, thanks for listening.
Now remember, if you have
any questions or comments,
please visit our website
at www.EnglishPod.com.
- Right, Erica and I are always
there to answer all the questions,
and we really like to receive
comments and suggestions
from all our users, so be sure to
go and leave us your comments.
- Okay, Marco, it's been fun.
- Yes, it has, but sadly,
we have to go now.
So until next time, it's goodbye.
(upbeat music)